Guide to the Sir William Watson papers, 1892-1935 MS 385
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
William Watson papers
1892-1935
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Watson, William, Sir
MS 385
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
This collection contains the correspondence, manuscript verse, and proofs of poems of the poet Sir William Watson. Correspondents include R. Ellis Roberts, Clarence Winchester (of the Amalgamated Press), and T.N. Green-Armytage.
Biographical / Historical
Sir William Watson was born in 1858 at Burley-in-Wharfedale, Yorkshire. His first published poem appeared in the "Liverpool Argus." His poetry was often inspired by art or politics, in which he was very interested in. After the death of his father, he fell into financial difficulties, and hoped to be named to the office of Poet Laureate. This, however, never occurred. In 1890, William became famous with the poem "Wordsworth's Grave." In 1909, he married Miss Adeline Maureen Pring, who urged him to publish his poems. He was knighted in 1917, and died in August 1935.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the correspondence, manuscript verse, and proofs of poems of the poet Sir William Watson. Correspondents include R. Ellis Roberts, Clarence Winchester (of the Amalgamated Press), and T.N. Green-Armytage. Also included is a typescript written by Lady Watson describing how she was accosted by a retired Scotland Yard detective.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was purchased from C.C. Kohler with Friends on Fondren funds in 1972.
Index Terms
Subjects
English literature -- 20th century; Authors
Document Types
poems; letters (correspondence); clippings (information artifacts)
- Series I: Works and newsclippings, 185032 (Box 1)
  - Preliminary page proofs for Lyric Love, [1982]; 37816; Watson, William, Sir; 0 Linear Feet
  - Newsclippings regarding Watson, 1895-1935; 49426
  - Contents list for Selected Poems, 1903; 49427
  - Correspondence: Watson to Prof. Grierson, Nov. 14, 1916; 49428
  - Poem: "Catullus CI, Version", 1921; 49429
  - Poem: "The Great Misgiving (Wm. Watson" by G.G.M., 1921; 49430
  - Correspondence: Watson to R. Ellis Roberts, April 16, 1923; 49431
  - Correspondence: Watson to Clarence Winchester, 1928-1929; 49432
  - Correspondence: Watson, Lady Watson to T.N. Green-Armytage, 1931-1934; 49433
  - Typescript: "The Happening" by Lady Maureen Watson, Dec. 12, 1932; 49434
  - Poem: "Lines" (to M.R.C. with Poems), n.d.; 49435